Bye-bye.
네, 그럼...
I just got reservations
at Michelle's...
약혼 후 처음 맞는
크리스마스를
뜻깊게 보내려고
미셸에 예약하고
and tickets to The Music Man
to celebrate...
뮤직 맨 공연 티켓도 샀어
our first holiday
as a betrothed couple.
- '약혼'
- 약혼한 커플
-"Betrothed."
-Betrothed couple.
- 안녕!
피비?
Phoebe?
웬 해골?
Skull?
아, 우리 엄마 거야
Yeah, it's my mom's.
끔찍해라!
Oh, my God!
엄마 해골이 아니라
No, no, no. It's not my mom.
엄마가 갖고 계시던 거야
It belonged to my mom.
크리스마스에도
사람들이 죽는다는 걸
She used to put it out
every Christmas...
상기시키려고
꺼내놓곤 하셨거든
to remind us that even though
it's Christmas, people still die.
거기 먹을 걸 담아도 돼
And you can put candy in it.
- 안녕
먹을래?
Licorice?
좋지
Sure.
- 올 핸 내가 벤을 볼 거야
- 잘 됐네!
-I get Ben for the holidays this year.
-That's great!
- 산타 옷 입을 거야?
- 아니
-Are you gonna dress up as Santa?
-Nope.
수잔이 매년 그렇게
하는 거 아는데
I know Susan does every year.
올해는 하누카에 대해
가르치려고
I want to take this year
to teach him about Hanukkah.
그럼 난 벤한테
And maybe I could teach Ben...
크리스마스 해골과
죽음에 대해 가르쳐야겠다
about the Christmas skull
and how people die.
벤한테 피비에 대해
먼저 가르쳐야겠다
You may need to use this year
to teach Ben about Phoebe.
안녕
- 쟤 안에 있는 거 알았어?
- 아니
-Did you know he was in there?
-No.
-How long have we been home?
-About half an hour.
- 우리 언제 집에 왔지?
- 30분 전에
좋아라
Lovely.
The One With The Holiday Armadillo
'센트럴 퍼크'
내 생각 좀 들어 봐
우리 결혼하면...
You know what I was thinking?
When we get married, will you...
자기 성을 '빙'으로
바꿀 거야?
change your name to "Bing"?
아니
No.
왜?
Why not?
'빙'은 이상해
Bing's weird.
Oh, hey, you guys.
안녕, 얘들아
집주인이 전화했는데
집수리 거의 끝났대
My landlord just called.
My apartment's gonna be ready soon.
I guess I'll be moving out.
곧 방 빼줄게
피비, 좀 서운하다
Phoebe, I'm gonna miss you.
그럼, 서운하겠지
Yes, you will be very sad.
- 레이첼한테 말해야지
- 둘이 같이 살게?
-I gotta go tell Rachel the good news.
-You'll be living together again?
- 왜, 어때서?
- 조이랑 재밌게 사니까
-Why not?
-She's having so much fun with Joey...
그냥 거기서
살 줄 알았거든
I assumed she'd still
be living with him.
어째서 조이랑 재미있게
산다고 생각하는데?
Why do you think
she's having so much fun?
그냥, 레이첼이
No reason, except she...
말해줬으니까
told me.
그래? 나랑 같이
살기 싫다고 하던?
She said she didn't want
to live with me?
아냐, 그런 말 안 했어
No. No, she didn't say that.
이제 모니카하고 얘기해라
I think you should talk to Monica now.
걱정 마, 레이첼은
너와 같이 살 거야
Phoebe, I'm sure
she wants to live with you.
그럴까? 정말 확실해?
You're absolutely sure?
확실하진 않지만
십중팔구 그럴 걸
No, but I'll bet she probably does.
십중팔구?
Oh, probably?
난 그 말 싫어
I don't like that word.
'십중팔구'가 무슨
뜻인지 잘 알지
I know what "probably" really means.
Yeah, yeah.
'너희 엄만 십중팔구
자살 안 하실 거다'
"Oh, your mom
probably won't kill herself."
I'm sorry,
but I'm not hanging my hopes...
미안하지만 레이첼과
같이 살고 싶은 소망을
그 놈의 '십중팔구'에
의지할 순 없어
of Rachel and I living together
on "probably."
You gotta take care of yourself
in this world.
믿을 건 자신뿐이라구
History teaches us nothing.
역사가 가르치긴
뭘 가르쳐?
Bing doesn't seem so weird now,
does it?
이젠 '빙'도 별로
어색하진 않지?
You're home.
잘 됐다, 집에 있었네
피비가 크리스마스 선물로
뭘 사줬게?
Guess what Phoebe got me
for Christmas?
-Drums?
-No, drums!
- 드럼?
- 아니, 드럼!
안녕하세요, 브리토 둘
포장해 주실래요?
Could we get
two burritos to go, please?
죄송해요, 나처럼 같이
사는 사람도 있잖아요
I'm sorry. But not that sorry,
you don't have to live with it.
챈들러 빙이란 이름으로
예약했어요
We have a reservation under Bing.
45분만 기다리세요
Okay, we'll have a table for you
in about 45 minutes.
45분이요?
8시에 뮤직맨 봐야하는데
We have tickets
to The Music Man at 8.
죄송해요, 크리스마스엔
아주 바쁘거든요
I'm sorry.
Christmas is a very busy time, sir.
내가 농담해서 그런 거요?
Is this because of the burrito thing?
- 돈 좀 쥐어줘
- 돈을? 농담했다고?
-You need to give him money.
-It was a joke!
아니, 테이블 말야
악수하는 척하고 줘
To get a table. Places like this
are always shaking you down.
- 뇌물은 다 좋아하거든
- 좋아, 진정하라고
-Everybody wants a payoff.
-All right, calm down, O'Malley.
- 슬쩍 쥐어주고 올게
- 너무 티나지 않게 해
-I'll slip him some money.
-But you've got to be smooth.
나도 할 수 있어
Hey, I can be smooth.
좀 바빠서 그런데
테이블 좀 빨리 주면
We're in a hurry.
If you could get us a table...
a bit quicker, I'd appreciate it.
아주 고맙겠는데요
- 그러죠
- 좋아요
-Of course, sir.
-Okay.
- 어떻게 됐어?
- 돈이 딴 손에 있었어
-How'd it go?
-Had the money in the wrong hand.
넌 토할 것처럼
You don't feel...
- 속이 울렁거리지 않니?
- 아니
-Like you're gonna throw up?
-No.
난 그래, 그러니...
Well, I do. So let's...
저, 벤...
So, Ben, you...
곧 무슨 날이 오는 지
너도 알지?
You know what holiday is coming up?
크리스마스요
Christmas.
그래, 그거말고
다른 날도 있잖아
Yeah, and you know what
other holiday is coming up?
크리스마스 이브요
Christmas Eve.
그래, 그런데...
Yes, but also...
하누카도 있지!
Hanukkah!
너도 반은 유대인이고
하누카는 유대명절이야
See, you're part Jewish
and Hanukkah is a Jewish holiday.
산타는 나는 사슴도 있어요
Santa has reindeers that can fly.
맞아, 근데 하누카땐...
Right, but on Hanukkah..
하누카는 기적을
기념하는 날이야
Hanukkah is a celebration
of a miracle.
옛날, 옛적에 마카베족이
살고 있었는데
Years and years ago there were
these people called the Maccabees.
좋아, 그래
Okay, that's right. Yes...
그런데 하누카 때는...
but on Hanukkah, we sing:
이건 시합이 아냐
Okay, it's not a contest.
산타는 언제 와요?
When is Santa coming?
올해는 산타 대신에
How about this year,
instead of Santa...
하누카를 축하하는 게 어때?
we have fun celebrating Hanukkah?
산타할아버진 안 오세요?
No Santa?
내가 나쁜 애라서요?
Was I bad?
아냐, 넌 착한 애야
아주 착한 애지
No, no, no, you weren't bad.
You've been very good, Ben.
- 산타가 화났군요
- 아냐, 그런 거 아냐
-Santa's mad at me.
-No, hey, hey, come on.
산타는 너한테 화 안 났어
알았어?
Ben, Santa is not mad at you, okay?
널 얼마나 좋아하시는데
You're his favorite little guy.
그럼 산타할아버지 오세요?
So Santa's coming?
물론이지!
Yes!
산타할아버지 오신다
Santa's coming.
쉬워, 아무렇지 않게
It's easy. Just keep it casual.
말을 건네며 악수를 하고
돈을 주는 거지
Shake his hand and give him the money.
- 어떻게 그렇게 잘 알아?
- 나도 몰라
-How do you know so much about this?
-I don't know.
리차드가 하던 거구나?
Richard used to do it, didn't he?
지금쯤은 스프라도
먹고 있었을 걸
We'd be eating our soup right now.
콧수염난 얼간이
Mustached bastard.
저 사람들 방금 일어섰어
빨리 돈주고 와
Those people just left. Come on.
Quick, give him the money.
실례합니다
Excuse me.
좀 바빠서 그러는데
자리 좀...?
그래, 너 드럼 좋아하는구나
So you like the drums.
잘됐네
That's great.
사실 난 그것 때문에
문제가 안될까
I was worried that
they would create maybe...
걱정했는데
an unbearable living situation.
지금보니 아니네
잘 됐다!
But, okay, well, apparently not.
So, yay!
피비, 우리 노래도
하나 배웠어
Hey, we already learned a song.
준비?
하나, 둘, 셋, 넷
Ready? One, two, three, four.
테킬라!
Tequila!
재밌네
That's fun.
Here you go.
여기 있어요
Thank you, Gunther.
Put her there.
고마워요, 건터
받아 둬요
Definitely not easier with coins.
동전으론 잘 안 돼
-Thank you.
- 고마워
- 안녕, 피비
- 안녕
Hey, Phoebe.
자, 49달러 50센트 남았다
Here. Now I only owe you $49.50.
Hey, Phoebe...
이봐, 피비...
조이에게 건물을 혼란스럽게 할
선물을 주려거든
if you want to get Joey a gift
that disrupts the entire building...
why not something more subtle...
좀 더 색다른 걸로 줄걸
벽 부수는 공이나
Like a wrecking ball...
수두 바이러스 약병
같은 거 말야
or a vial of small pox
to release in the hallway?
It's not just the drum noise.
Every five minutes...
드럼 소음뿐만 아니라
5분 간격으로
조이가 공중에
스틱을 던졌다가
Joey throws his sticks
in the air...
'아, 내 눈! 내 눈!'
하는 소릴 들어야 돼
and I have to hear:
"Oh, my eye! Oh, God, my eye!"
-I mean, it's so annoying.
-Yes, thank you.
- 신경 거슬려 죽겠다고
- 그래, 고마워
You see, this is how normal people
are supposed to react to drums.
거 봐, 이게 보통 사람이 하는
드럼에 대한 반응이라고!
You got Joey drums to annoy Rachel...
피비, 그럼 조이한테
드럼을 사준 건
레이첼이 거기 살기
싫게 만들려고 한 거야?
so she wouldn't want
to live there anymore?
Maybe on some level.
좀 그런 생각도 있었지
You could just not throw the sticks
up in the air.
조이, 공중에 스틱을
안 던지면 되잖아
What is rock 'n' roll about that?
록앤롤은 그런 거야
Hey, Joey, I got you another present.
조이, 선물 또 사왔어
Hold it!
Before you tell me what it is...
잠깐?
내가 한 번 맞춰볼께
좋아, 뭐야?
Okay, what is it?
그건 말야
It's a...
타란튤라야!
tarantula!
God, Rachel, I'm sorry.
What was I thinking...
맙소사, 레이첼, 미안해
내 생각이 모자랐어
giving Joey this big, gross,
scary spider...
조이한테 이런 크고
징그러운 걸 주다니
in such a poorly constructed cage?
박스도 허술한데
What are you talking about?
I love them.
무슨 소리야?
나 거미 좋아해
어렸을 때 키웠는데
고양이가 먹어 버렸어
I had a tarantula when I was a kid.
But it died because my cat ate it.
그리고 고양이도 죽었지
And then my cat died.
But, Joey, isn't this cool?
조이, 멋있지?
Is it on me?
I feel like it's on me. I got..
나한테 붙었냐?
꼭 기어다니는 것 같아
Oh, isn't that adorable?
너무 귀엽지?
Joey is afraid of the tarantula.
타란튤라가 무서운가봐
He's so adorable.
정말 귀여워
너무 재밌는 애야
He's so much fun.
조이가 최고지
재밌다니 좋겠다
I'm glad you're having
so much fun here.
Wait a minute.
잠깐만
What's the matter?
왜 그래?
Our apartment is ready.
아파트 수리 끝났대
And that makes you angry because...?
그런데 왜 화가 났니?
Because you'd rather
live here with Joey.
네가 조이랑 사는 걸
좋아하니까
-Where did you get that?
-Monica and Chandler...
- 누가 그런 소릴 해?
- 모니카와 챈들러가
네가 여기서
재미있게 산다고...
said you were having
so much fun here...
드럼이나 타란튤라도
방해 못 할 것 같다
and apparently no amount of drums
or tarantula is gonna change that.
피비, 그럼 조이한테
이런 선물한 게
Did you get all this stuff for Joey...
to try to drive me out
of the apartment?
날 내보내려고
그런 거야?
그럼 물고기를 사 주지
You might as well
have gotten him a fish.
You know how fish freak me out.
난 물고기라면 질색이잖아
Fish.
물고기였어
But it wouldn't have mattered.
We're gonna live together.
그건 상관없어
우리 둘이 같이 살거니까
우린 룸메이트잖아
That's the deal.
Yes, but I wanted you to want
to live with me.
그래, 그렇지만
진심으로 그러길 바래
그렇지만 여기서
사는 게 재밌다면...
But if you're having
so much fun over here..
It's so much more fun with you.
너랑 사는게 더 재밌어
-We did have fun, didn't we?
-We did.
- 재미 있었지?
- 그럼 아주 재미있었지
They say, if we want,
we could see it tonight.
어쨌건, 원하면
오늘 밤에 볼 수 있대
- 정말 보고 싶다
- 와 신난다!
-I would love to.
-Yay, okay!
- 좋아
- 잘 됐어, 좋아
-Good, good, good.
-Great. All right. Good.
모니카가
드럼 좀 그만 치래
And Monica asked me
to make the drumming stop.
됐어
Done.
'할로윈 의상 대여점'
어서오세요
바지 돌려주러 오셨어요?
Hello, sir.
You here to return those pants?
아뇨, 제 바지예요
No, these are my pants.
그렇군요
Okay.
- 그래 어떻게 오셨죠?
- 산타 옷 있어요?
-How can I help you?
-Do you have a Santa outfit left?
크리스마스 이틀 전에요?
없는데요
Two days before Christmas?
Sorry, man.
그럼 크리스마스
분위기 나는 다른 건요?
Okay, look.
Do you have anything Christmas-y?
아들하고 약속했는데
무척 실망할 거예요
I promised my son, and I really
don't want to disappoint him.
뭐든 있을 거 아녜요?
Come on, you gotta have something.
I'm the Holiday Armadillo!
난 아마딜로다!
I'm a friend of Santa's...
난 산타 친구인데
and he sent me here to wish you...
산타가 보냈단다
너의
a merry Christmas!
즐거운 크리스마스를 위해!
What happened to Santa,
Holiday Armadillo?
산타할아버진 어디 계시니,
아마딜로?
Santa was unavailable...
크리스마스가 가까워서
so close to Christmas.
그분은 너무 바쁘세요
Come in, have a seat.
들어와서 앉아
You must be exhausted,
coming all the way from Texas.
텍사스에서 오느라
힘들었을 텐데
-Texas?
-That's right, Ben.
- 텍사스요?
- 그렇단다, 벤
I'm Santa's representative...
난 남부지역을 맡고있는
for all the Southern states.
산타의 조수거든
And Mexico!
멕시코하고!
But Santa sent me here...
산타할아버지가
to give you these presents, Ben.
이 선물을 보내셨단다
Maybe the lady will help me
with these presents.
고모가 좀
도와주실 거야
Wow, thanks!
와, 고마워요!
You're welcome, Ben.
천만에, 벤
Merry Christmas.
메리 크리스마스
And happy Hanukkah!
그리고 해피 하누카!
하누카도요?
난 유대인이기도 하대요
Are you for Hanukkah too?
Because I'm part Jewish.
너도? 나도야
You are? Me too.
Because armadillos
also wandered in the desert?
아마딜로도 사막을
헤매고 다니니까?
You want to wander in the hall?
넌 복도 좀 헤매고
다녀볼래?
Hey, Ben!
이봐, 벤!
What if the Holiday Armadillo...
이 아마딜로가
told you all about
the Festival of Lights?
빛의 축제 얘길 해주면
어떨까?
Cool!
좋아요!
Come on, Ben.
이리 와, 벤
Years and years ago...
옛날 옛적에...
there were these people called...
마카베 족이라 불리는
-the Maccabees!
-Ho, ho, ho!
- 사람들이 있었단다!
- 호, 호, 호!
Merry Christmas!
메리 크리스마스!
Santa!
- 산타할아버지!
- 안녕!
What are you doing here, Santa?
여긴 웬 일이세요, 산타?
Well, I'm here to see
my old buddy, Ben.
내 오랜 친구,
벤을 만나러 왔지
그러는 넌 뭐하는 거냐
What are you doing here...
이상한 거북 인간?
Weird Turtle Man?
I'm the Holiday Armadillo...
전 아마딜로예요
your part-Jewish friend.
유대인 친구잖아요
벤한테 선물 주라고
저를 보내셨잖아요
You sent me here
to give Ben some presents.
Remember?
기억 나세요?
What?
뭐?
Did you bring me any presents, Santa?
선물 가져오셨어요?
You bet I did, Ben.
물론 가져왔지, 벤
Put her there.
받아 둬
손이 저렇게 작지 않았음
받을 수 있었을 텐데
Well, it would have worked this time
if his hands weren't so damn small.
Ho, ho, ho!
호, 호, 호!
벤, 선물을 더
열어보지 그러니
Ben, come open more gifts.
The armadillo and I
will have a talk in the kitchen.
산타, 아마딜로와 우리 셋이
부엌에서 얘기 좀 해요
이런 말을 하게 될 줄은
몰랐는데
There's a sentence
I never thought I'd say.
뭐 하는 거야?
What are you doing?
You said you were having trouble
finding a Santa costume...
네가 전화해서 산타 옷
못 빌린다고 하길래
so I borrowed one
from a guy at work.
직장 동료한테 하나 빌려왔지
Thank you, but you gotta leave.
고맙지만 가줘야겠어
-Why?
-Because...
- 왜?
- 왜냐하면
I'm finally getting him excited
about Hanukkah...
이제 겨우 하누카에
관심을 보였는데
and you're wrecking it.
네가 망치고 있어
아직 배도 흔들어보지
못 했잖아
But I didn't get to shake my belly
like a bowlful of jelly.
I'm sorry, Chandler,
but this is really important to me.
미안하다, 챈들러
나한텐 중요한 일이거든
Fine, I'll give the suit back.
좋아, 옷 돌려주지 뭐
Hey, you think you can keep it
another night?
하룻밤 더 빌리면
안 될까?
Santa, really?
산타를? 진심이야?
Yeah, is that okay?
그래도 괜찮겠어?
Did your dad ever dress up like Santa?
아버님이 산타 옷
입으신 적 있어?
-No.
-Then it's okay!
- 아니
- 그럼 좋아!
Okay, Ben. Santa has to go.
좋아, 벤
산타할아버지 가신대
Say goodbye.
인사드려
No, why does he have to go?
왜 가셔야 돼요?
산타와 아마딜로가
Because if Santa and the Holiday...
Armadillo...
너무 오래
are ever in the same room
for too long...
같은 방에 있으면
the universe will implode!
우주가 폭발하거든!
Merry Christmas!
메리 크리스마스!
No, why can't the armadillo leave?
I want Santa.
아마딜로더러 가라고 해요
난 산타가 좋아요
Fine, I give up. Santa..
좋아, 포기했다, 산타...
Santa can stay!
산타 할아버진 있어도 돼
Well, I'll stay...
하누카 얘길 해 주면
안 가고 남아 있으마
but only because I want to hear
about Hanukkah.
Ben, will you sit here with Santa...
벤, 여기 할아버지와 앉아서
and learn about Hanukkah?
하누카 얘기 들을까?
Okay, Santa.
좋아요
- 고마워
- 별 소릴
-Thank you.
-You're welcome.
All right, it's time...
좋아, 그럼 이제
for the story of Hanukkah.
하누카 얘길 해줄게
Years and years ago...
옛날 옛적에
there were these people
called the Maccabees!
마카베 족이란
사람들이 있었단다!
Merry Christmas!
메리 크리스마스!
와, 여기 좀 봐!
Oh, wow, look at this place!
Oh, this is terrible.
이럴수가
They've made so many changes...
너무 많이 바뀌어서
할머니의 체취를 이젠
느낄 수가 없네
I can't even feel
my grandmother's presence anymore.
Oh, new sconces!
와, 새 촛대네!
-Oh, my God!
-What?
- 세상에!
- 왜?
Remember how you told me
your grandmother put up that wall...
너 기억나? 할머니가
칸막이를 세워서 방을
-to make that into two bedrooms?
-Yeah.
- 두 개로 만들었댔잖아
- 그래
And that the landlord
might find out...
집주인이 알고는
그 칸막이를
-and then tear it down?
-Yeah?
- 허물 수도 있지 않을까?
- 그래?
정말 내가 무슨 말 하는 지
모르겠어
Do you really not know
where I'm going?
없어졌어, 방이 하나야
It left. It's one huge room.
Oh, no!
이런!
와!
Wow!
거 봐
See?
칸막이를 다시 세워야겠다
I guess we'll have to
put the wall back up.
- 천장에 창이 있어서 안 돼
- 천장에 창이 있어?
-You can't, with the new skylight.
-There's a skylight?
와!
Wow!
그럼 어떡하지?
아파트를 새로 구할까?
So should we start looking
for a new place?
있잖아, 할머니가
You know, I'm sensing...
별로 안 좋아하실 것 같거든
that my grandmother
would not be comfortable with that.
그래?
Oh, yeah?
이젠 할머니의 체취가
느껴지기 시작해?
Starting to feel her again there,
are we?
- 조금
- 그렇군
-A little bit. Yeah.
-Yeah.
피비, 할머니가 너 혼자
살라고 하시진 않니?
Is your grandmother maybe saying
that you should live here alone?
너도 들었어?
너 재주 좋다
You heard it too? You have the gift.
피비, 괜찮아
Phoebe, it's okay.
나 조이랑 살아도 돼
I like living with Joey.
- 정말이야?
- 그럼, 짐싸기도 싫고
-Are you sure?
-Please. I hate packing...
직장도 가깝잖아
it's closer to work.
재밌기도 하고
And we do have fun.
너와 같이 못 살아서
정말 안타깝지만 말야
Although, I'm really gonna miss
living with you.
- 나도
- 나도 알아
-Oh, me too.
-I know.
잠깐, 저 소리 들었어?
Did you hear that?
너희 할머니가
뭐라고 하시는데
I'm getting something
from your grandmother.
혼자 아파트에서
살게 됐으니
She said since you get to keep
the one-bedroom apartment...
보라색 의자 레이첼
주라고 하시는데
you should give Rachel
the purple chair.
아니, 난 못 들었어
No, I do not hear that.
하루 밖에 못 쓰는
And the miracle was that
that little bit of oil...
아주 적은 양의 기름을
기적적으로
that should have lasted
just one day, burned for....
- 8일이나 썼단다
- 맞아
-Eight whole days.
-That's right.
그래서 하누카를
기념하는 거야, 끝
And that's why we celebrate
Hanukkah today. The end.
- 멋진데요
- 그래
-Awesome.
-Yeah.
수퍼맨이 이집트에서
My favorite part...
유대인을 구출하는
장면이 젤 재밌어요
was when Superman
flew all the Jews out of Egypt.
아마딜로는 그 부분
별로라고 생각하는데
The armadillo was actually
not so thrilled about that part.
벤, 이제 하누카
Okay, Ben, it's time to light...
촛불을 밝힐 시간이야!
the Hanukkah candles!
안녕
와! 오늘 꼭 부활절 토끼
장례식날 같다
Wow! Looks like the Easter Bunny's
funeral in here.
어서 와
초에 불붙이고 있었어
Come on, come on.
We're lighting the candles.
수퍼맨은 이해하는데
I understand why Superman is here...
토끼 장례식에
웬 고슴도치?
but why is there a porcupine
at the Easter Bunny's funeral?
- 잡았어?
- 잡았어
-You get it?
-I got it.
Back in the cage?
우리에 넣었어?
It's back in the cage.
그래 넣었어
유리 문 닫았어?
Is the cage closed?
조이, 어린애처럼
굴지 말고 어서 나와!
Joey, will you just come out here
and stop being such a baby!